Okay everyone so
what we had on Sunday evening we went online for just a
few minutes with דף ל"א עמוד ב' Daf Lamed-Aleph Amud Bet and
the reason I left this for today although it
was just online was not only it takes a few minutes to
explain but also because it is a point to a very central
debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot that we have referred to
in the past and here we're finally getting to it although we'll
see a parallel one tomorrow as well. So if you remember yesterday
after discussing the issue about doing the שחיטה shechita in two or
three places like not with a single cut and the cut has
to be continuous and then the פסול psul of חלדה chalada דריסה
dreesa which is if you're burrowing if you did not start from
the outside and cut in but you started in the middle and
cut out or something of that nature or cut in the wrong
opposite direction we had and then there was questions about let's say
you even did it under the skin but you know not between
the two סימנים simanim or even under the wool and so on
so we had a little discussion of the פסול דריסה psul dreesa
we have this last line here I mean פסול psul excuse me
did I say דריסה? dreesa? I meant חלדה. chalada. Excuse me דריסה
dreesa is pressuring but this issue about cutting between the סימנים simanim
in the wrong direction and starting in the middle this פסול psul
of burrowing is חלדה. chalada. We have the following line to wrap
this up: בעי רב פפא Ba'ei Rav Papa so רב פפא Rav
Papa asked כי חלדה במיעוט סימנים מה? ki chalda bemiut simanim mah?
What happens if the person does burrowing in the minority of the
סימנים? simanim? And the answer is תיקו teyku we don't know. Okay
that does not sound too complicated but what does it mean? So
רש"י Rashi says what it means is you did the first let's
say you know סימן siman correctly let's say it's a בהמה behema
the first סימן siman
and sixty percent of the next סימן siman correctly. Okay so you
think you're done but then what you did is to cut the
last part of the last סימן siman you did a burrowing you
stuck your knife in the middle and cut in the opposite direction.
Okay or let's say it was a bird and you did the
same thing you cut the first סימן siman sixty percent you think
you're done but then for the last forty percent you stuck your
knife between the two סימנים simanim and you cut that forty percent
again in the opposite direction from between the two סימנים simanim down
rather than outside. What's the הלכה? halacha? And according to רש"י Rashi
this is a general question about the issue about the remainder after
you've done the רוב. rov. We say רובו ככולו rubo kekulo we
say that if you do the majority it's like you've done the
whole thing you don't have to do anymore but according to רש"י
Rashi okay but that's ככולו. kekulo. What happens if you actually do
one hundred percent? Does the last forty-nine percent is that part of
the act or not? Or do we say as soon as you've
done fifty-one percent you're over? And for רש"י Rashi that's what this
question is and רש"י Rashi ties this in to questions that the
גמרא Gemara raised before and the גמרא Gemara will raise after. If
you remember the גמרא Gemara raised before when it dealt with the
problem of הגרמה hagrama about going you know a third down and
then you did a top third and then you did a bottom
third and like you know some part in the middle was done
wrong and it also had even let's say you did two thirds
correctly and the last third you did in too high of a
place. So רש"י Rashi says that's a similar question and we're going
to see tomorrow a question about what happens if you do שהייה
shehiya you pause in the last part of the cutting. And in
all of those things רש"י Rashi says it's all the same question.
And the question is that although if you stopped right now it
would be good שחיטה shechita you've done sixty you know רוב rov
of the סימן siman or if it's a בהמה behema one you
know רוב rov of two סימנים simanim and if you stopped now
you'd be fine if you went ahead and finished it and you
finished it incorrectly maybe that invalidates everything. And the גמרא Gemara leaves
it as a תיקו teyku and since it leaves it as a
תיקו teyku we don't know we would rule strictly. So that for
רש"י Rashi is the question and the conceptual issue as we said
from the beginning is that when you say fifty-one percent is enough
are you saying that all הלכה halacha requires is fifty-one percent? Everything
afterwards is not even part of the act of שחיטה? shechita? Or
you saying no in principle הלכה halacha requires one hundred percent but
fifty-one percent is as if you did the one hundred percent but
if you go ahead and do the one hundred percent right then
that's all part of the act and therefore any פסול psul even
in that last part is going to invalidate. That's how רש"י Rashi
understands the question he says it would have been an equal question
across all the פסולים psulim and we have to פוסקן posken strictly
because גמרא Gemara says תיקו. teyku. רש"י Rashi even says not here
but in tomorrow's דף daf well I'm not even see it today
again depending on how quickly we do it that that has very
practical implications. רש"י Rashi says you know some of the people that
might object aren't here now so maybe good I'll get it under
the radar רש"י Rashi says let's say you're cutting you're שחט shechting
the chicken or the בהמה behema and you've שחט shechted רוב rov
of the סימנים simanim and you see though that it's taking a
long time for it to die and it's suffering and you want
to go ahead and you know put it out of its misery
רש"י Rashi says don't meaning you did the שחיטה shechita a minute
ago רש"י Rashi says don't now go back and finish cutting to
put it out of its misery because then there's a פסול שהייה
psul shehiya right because even though now it's a good שחיטה shechita
because that would be a שהייה במיעוט בתרא shehiya bemiut batra it'll
be a שהייה shehiya in the last minority. So now that you've
gone and continued the שחיטה shechita that becomes part of the שחיטה
shechita and that would invalidate. Then you can do it right after
right? Well that's the... רש"י Rashi says if you want to put
it out of its misery, so, you know, just chop its head
off or cut it from the, right, or cut it from the
opposite angle, you know, back of the neck or whatever, but don't
do it, continue the שחיטה shechita because even though that's the point
of this גמרא Gemara that the last minority if you go ahead
and do it might be considered part of the whole process and
invalidate. תוספות, Tosafot, this big תוספות, Tosafot, quotes רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
who rejects that. He says no, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says it's
absolutely not true. Anything in the last minority does not count and
anything in the last minority is not part of the שחיטה shechita
act and therefore what רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says, the question in
the גמרא Gemara about חלדה במיעוט סימנים chalada bemiut simanim is the
following case. It says remember we talked about חלדה chalada which is
if you go between the two סימנים, simanim, right, and you cut.
Right, so you're starting, you've burrowed between the two סימנים. simanim. According
to תוספות Tosafot the question is let's say the burrowing is only
within one סימן. siman. You have your one סימן siman here and
you pierce your knife through that סימן siman and you have a
מיעוט miut right that is below your knife. And then you cut.
Is that okay? Right? Remember if you have your two סימנים simanim
and you cut between the סימנים simanim and the skin according to
one opinion that's okay because you're not burrowing between the סימנים simanim
and then you cut up you're fine. You don't have to start
from the outside of the skin. What if instead of going between
the two סימנים simanim and the skin down here you went into
the first סימן siman but only into the minority of the first
סימן siman and then you cut up? Okay, is that considered burrowing
or not because you only have a minority of the סימן siman
below you? So that's how רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam chooses to read
this גמרא. Gemara. He reads the other גמרא Gemara differently but the
more important point is is that רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam rejects the
problem that the last minority would ever be an issue. So you
really have here on this little one line of the גמרא Gemara
a very key debate of רש"י Rashi and רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam.
רש"י Rashi says that even though the שחיטה shechita is done when
you do the majority of the סימן siman or the two סימנים,
simanim, if you continue and finish it that becomes incorporated into the
act of שחיטה shechita and an invalidity in that additional thing that
you did that you didn't have to do but now that you
did it became part of the שחיטה shechita that could invalidate. That's
what the גמרא Gemara says תיקו teiku but we have to be
concerned that it does invalidate. And תוספות Tosafot according to רבינו תם
Rabbeinu Tam says no, once you've done the majority anything afterwards is
not part of the שחיטה. shechita. So this is a general question:
when is
the problem of
חלדה chalada according to רבינו תם? Rabbeinu Tam? I told you it's
when you did you started you did the חלדה chalada within a
סימן. siman. It has nothing to do with finishing or not finishing
whatever.
No no, when is it really a problem according to everybody?
Oh, when you do between the two סימנים simanim
and you don't cut any of it?
Or no you do, but you start between the two סימנים simanim
and you cut a majority of both? Oh yeah exactly exactly.
So anyway so according to רש"י Rashi and רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
at least by this case of שחיטה shechita but it could be
asked as a general question when we say רובו ככולו rubo kekulo
do we say that when we say רוב rov is enough it
means it's just enough, all הלכה halacha requires is רוב rov and
anything afterwards is immaterial? Or do we say רוב rov counts as
if you've done the whole thing, but if you go ahead and
do the whole thing then even what you've done in the remaining
forty-nine percent is part of that act and any problems can actually
be it could be more of a problem because you've finished incorrectly
than if you hadn't finished at all which is what רש"י Rashi
says. Yes.
Does this relate to yesterday's discussion about process and when do we
define the end of it?
Yeah it could, meaning you know clearly because we're looking at it
as a process you know we could say that even though it
could have ended here if you continue it it becomes incorporated into
the act. So it could be but there's even a question but
not necessarily, you could say even if it's a process the process
ends as soon as you've done enough.
Anything after that that could be defined as the end.
Right, right, it's
the complement of yesterday's discussion. Right, yesterday's discussion was about
the מיעוט בתרא miut batra of yesterday's discussion. I did it again.
I said it's the מיעוט בתרא miut batra of yesterday's discussion the
last which is okay anyway I'm being funny right?
Okay, so from yesterday's discussion we got to a point and then
we looked retrospectively at prior actions. Right. Here you're getting to the
same point and now you're looking prospectively.
That's an interesting perspective so yeah surely.
More general question: this is not the only time where רבינו תם
Rabbeinu Tam disagrees with his grandfather?
That is correct.
So did he have a different teacher? Did he have another מסורה?
mesorah? Did he just have different?
No well even רש"י Rashi in general it raises a question, you
know, even רש"י Rashi and actually this comes up a good amount
in קדשים Kodashim will sometimes say things like when he explains something
he'll say לא שמעתי lo shamati which is like I didn't hear
of an explanation of what this גמרא Gemara is but here's what
I think or sometimes even more interesting he'll say, this is the
explanation that I received, שמעתי, shamati, but I don't it doesn't seem
correct and here's what I think the גמרא Gemara really means. And
that's certainly so, not everybody was sort of limited by the tradition,
by the explanation they had from tradition. Part of the whole idea
of תורה שבעל פה Torah she'baal peh is, you know, you bring
your own intellect to the to the text, to the material. And
certainly that was רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam's character, that רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam was extremely creative in his thoughts, so he was did not
feel constrained based on previous explanations if he didn't feel they were
correct. Okay, so now we are going to continue, so again that
is like one of the key debates about the concept of רובו
ככולו, rubo kekulo, but now we move on to the next
משנה. mishna. השוחט בשני ראשים כאחד שחיטתו. hashocheit bishnei roshim ke-echad shechitato.
it's okay. So you have a long knife and you cut two
heads, although you could imagine that we'd be concerned that if you're
cutting two heads, maybe you're putting pressure on them, but no, if
your knife is long enough and you've got the things laid down,
you can shecht without putting pressure on the drum. What?
Okay. שניים אוחזים בסכין ושוחטים. Shnayim ochazim basakin veshochtim. Now if two
people are holding a knife, and again, the simple sense of this
text, although this was yesterday's discussion, is that they're holding opposite ends
of the knife, it's like a saw, they've got it opposite, and
they shecht. ואפילו אחד למעלה ואחד למטה, Va'afilu echad lemala ve'echad lemata,
even one above and one below, they're in different, one is on
one side of the neck and the other is on the other
side of the neck. Okay, or if it's two separate knives, that
means one cutting one position and the other is cutting a different
position. But פשטות pashtus of this משנה mishna is that there are
two people holding a knife. שחיטתן כשרה, Shechitaton kesheira, it's valid, and
we're not concerned that just because they're holding opposite ends of the
knife that they put pressure on it. התיז את הראש בבת אחת,
Hitiz et harosh bebat achat, however, if you severed the head with
one
act, with one flick of the knife, then we heard this the
other day from Aaron, then אם יש בסכין מלא צוואר כשרה, Im
yeish basakin mlo tzavar kesheira, then, I'm sorry, did I skip a
line? פסולה, Psula, it is invalid. Why? Because if one thing totally
decapitates it, we assume that that's because you put too much pressure
on it, and therefore it's a problem of דרסה, drisa, of putting
on pressure. Okay. היה שוחט והתיז את הראש בבת אחת, Haya shocheit
vehitiz et harosh bebat achat, if you were shechting and
you did cut off the head in one movement, so meaning you
were shechting, meaning that you were doing it, you weren't doing a
chopping action, you actually were doing
a shechting action, a horizontal action.
So אם יש בסכין מלא צוואר, im yeish basakin mlo tzavar, so
if the סכין sakin has the length of a neck, כשרה, kesheira,
it's valid. What does that mean? So we're going to see the
way the גמרא Gemara explains what it means is that the length
of the knife is the length of the neck of the animal
you're shechting plus one additional neck length. And therefore, normally שחיטה shechita
requires you cut back and forth. Okay, two basically movements in order
to totally cut it. But if the knife was double length, so
even one movement will get you the same amount of cutting as
a back and forth because it cuts the whole neck length twice.
Thank you. And
therefore, in that case, it's okay even if the neck was severed
because as long as it severed through two lengths of a cut,
we're not concerned about דרסה. drisa. So if you chop off the
whole head, we are concerned about דרסה drisa unless it is a
double length, and therefore
you are, we are not, as long as you were doing a
horizontal movement and not a pressured movement.
Doesn't that speak to what we just had before? Almost החלי במיעוט
סימנים hichli bemiut simanim because you're still
if you're completing it incorrectly.
No, no, no, we're using it as evidence. If you chopped off
the head through doing a chopping motion, which is the first case
of דרסה. drisa. Or if you were doing a horizontal motion, but
your knife wasn't long enough, and you got all the way to
the back of the neck, in those types of cases, we're going
to assume that it's evidence that you were putting on pressure at
the beginning. It's not that you invalidated it because of the end,
it's looking at the whole action, we have evidence that you were
obviously putting on pressure from the very beginning. Okay, now.
But
if not, then
it's not, then you still could have done anything from the end.
Right. Unless you did the problem only at the end, then that
would be the debate of רש"י Rashi and רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam.
Okay, so it says like this.
במה דברים אמורים, Bamei devarim amurim, when is this true? בזמן שהוליך
ולא הביא, Bizman sheholich velo heivi, if you only, as I said,
did one motion. או הביא ולא הוליך, O heivi velo holich, or
you either brought without coming back, or you came back towards you
without going forward. Meaning you only did one motion. There, the knife
has to be double length. אבל
אם הוליך והביא, Aval im holich veheivi, but if you were moving
back and forth, אפילו כל שהוא אפילו באזמל כשרה, afillu kol shehu
afillu be'izmeil kesheira, even if the knife was the tiniest size and
even if it's the size of like an
awl, or even using an awl, it's kosher. So here's the question
about the length of the knife. On the one hand, there's a
concern about putting pressure, so you have to go ahead and if
you're just doing one motion, it has to be double the length.
Although interestingly, the משנה mishna mentions double the length
because of a case where you chopped off the head. It's not
so clear from the משנה mishna that you need double the length
if you didn't chop off the head. The משנה mishna at the
end of the משנה mishna says that if it's a smaller length,
it's okay even if it's less than the length of the neck,
it's a small length, it's okay as long as you do a
back and forth motion. So it's a little bit unclear, meaning just
the ambiguity of the משנה. mishna. The beginning of the משנה mishna
was solving the problem that the head got chopped off and we're
concerned about דרסה. drisa. And therefore it says that's solved if this
thing is a double length knife and you did one motion. The
end of the משנה mishna seems like we're no longer talking about
you chopping. chopped off the whole head and דרסה. Drisa. It sounds
like we're just talking about in a normal case of שחיטה, Shechita,
how long do you need the knife to be, right? And that's
normally how this משנה Mishnah is interpreted, right, that if a normal
case of שחיטה, Shechita, if you're do, you know, you need the
knife even forgetting chopping off the head, you need the life to
be the knife to be double length, but if you're not go,
but if you're not, if you're go, if you're going back and
forth, it could be even very small, because then you keep on
going back and forth until you actually cut through it. So by
the way, that is something that I think is not normally appreciated,
you know, in principle, you could,
you know, do a שחיטה Shechita like this, right, which does not
look like a normal act of שחיטה, Shechita, but you could go
back and forth and back and forth and back and forth, as
long as you're not applying pressure, you know, you're just slowly cutting
through the essentially sawing through the סימנים, Simanim, right, if you're not
applying pressure, that seems to be the point here at the end
of the משנה, Mishnah, as long as you know, that even a
כל שהוא Kol Shehu is valid. Yes, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי? Mena Hani Milei? Where do
these come from? אמר שמואל דאמר קרא, Amar Shmuel Damar Kra, meaning
where does this come from
that שחיטה Shechita is through, this is really the problem of the
פסול Psul of דרסה, Drisa, pressure, that שחיטה Shechita is through the
sharpness of the knife and through cutting, not through pressure. So אמר
שמואל דאמר קרא, Amar Shmuel Damar Kra, the verse says חץ שחוט
לשונם מרמה דיבר. Chetz Shachut Leshonam Mirma Diber.
Their tongue is like a cutting arrow, when they speak, you know,
deceit. So therefore, the same way an arrow cuts horizontally. Of course,
the point is which part of the arrow? I mean, if the
arrow's going into somebody, it's cutting through pressure and through stabbing. But
the גמרא Gemara somehow imagined that we're talking about the arrow hits
something sort of alongside its edge and therefore it's cutting through the
sharpness and not through pressure. וכן הוא אומר, Vechen Hu Omer, I'm
sorry,
תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana Debei Rabi Yishmael, they talk in the
house of רבי ישמעאל. Rabi Yishmael. ושחט, Veshachat, אין ושחט אלא ומשך.
Ein Veshachat Ela Umashach. ומשך Umashach means that you should draw the
knife, meaning horizontal. וכן הוא אומר, Vechen Hu Omer, and it says
זהב שחוט, Zahav Shachut, that you know, which is like sort of
like spun gold. So the same way if you imagine you're spinning
gold and you know, so it's sort of it's like stretching it
out. So it's talking about that type of horizontal motion. Okay. ואמר
חץ שחוט לשונם מרמה דיבר, Ve'amar Chetz Shachut Leshonam Mirma Diber, and
then this verse about the arrow. מאי ואומר? Mai Ve'omer? Why do
you need this verse about the arrow as well? וכי תימא זהב
שחוט, Vechi Teima Zahav Shachut, שחוט Shachut doesn't mean spun with the
word שחיטה. Shechita. The שין Shin is not part of the verb.
Maybe it means שנטוה כחוט. Shenitve Kechut.
So the שין Shin is not part of the verb. It means
gold שחוט Shechut which is made into strings. Maybe the שין Shin
is not part of the verb. So therefore תא שמע חץ שחוט
לשונם. Ta Shma Chetz Shachut Leshonam. So I'll quote you from this
other verse that we see this again, this idea about horizontal cutting.
רבא, Rava, now we're going to talk about an interesting story about
horizontal cutting. רבא הוה בדיק ליה גירא לרבי יונה בר תחליפא. Rava
Hava Badik Lei Girei Le'Rabi Yona Bar Tachlifa. רבא Rava would check
the arrows of רבי יונה בר תחליפא. Rabi Yona Bar Tachlifa. Remember
we said that the arrows were okay, was the verse we learned
it from. So apparently this רבי יונה בר תחליפא Rabi Yona Bar
Tachlifa was a hunter. So and here he was showing his שחיטה
Shechita knife to a חכם. Chacham. So he went and he showed
his arrows to רבא. Rava. ושחט בה עופא. Veshachat Bah Ofa. And
רבי יונה בר תחליפא Rabi Yona Bar Tachlifa would use this to
kill birds בהדי דפרח, Bahadi Deperach, as they were flying. So he
was,
he hunted pigeons or something and he threw, he shot an arrow
with them and the edge of the arrow, which was checked by
רבא, Rava, the edge of the arrow would cut the neck of
the bird. Now of course the question is going to be: How
do you know that it did correctly? Maybe it went through the
neck, right? Maybe,
so let's take, also you'd have to be a pretty amazing שוחט
Shochet to aim just for the neck of the bird. So anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says ודילמא עבד ליה חלדה? Udilma Avad Lei
Chalada? So maybe it exactly did this. Maybe it burrowed, meaning maybe
the point of the arrow went in and not the side of
the arrow. Right, which is so the גמרא Gemara says חזינן top
of
ל"א Lo, ע"א, חזינן גדפי דמפרמי. Chazinan Gidfei De'miframmei. No, we see
that the feathers, the neck feathers were basically were cut. So therefore,
if it went through the neck, right, you would not see the
underside, the neck feathers that were here. You could look at the
neck feathers here and see that they were cut by the arrow,
presumably from the outside in rather than from the inside out. So
you could inspect it and see that that happened. So the גמרא
Gemara says והבעי כיסוי? Ve'haba'ei Kisui? Okay, so maybe you שחט Shechted
it correctly. Where'd you do your כיסוי הדם? Kisui Hadam? It's a
bird. וכי תימא דמכסי ליה. Vechi Teima Demichasei Lei. Okay, you'll go
and you'll find where the bird dropped dead and then you'll do,
cover the blood. ואמר רבי זירא אמר רב, Ve'amar Rabi Zeira Amar
Rav, רבי זירא Rabi Zeira says in the name of רב, Rav,
השוחט
צריך שיתן עפר למטה ועפר למעלה. Hashochet Tzarich Sheyiten Afar Lemata Ve'afar
Lema'ala. You have to put dirt below and above. So wherever it
fell, you might be able to put the dirt above, but how
do you put the dirt below?
Was it dirty?
It was in a, well that's what it's going to say. שנאמר
וכסהו בעפר. Shene'emar Vechisahu Be'afar. You should cover it with dirt, in
the dirt. So ב Be is in the dirt. עפר לא נאמר.
Afar Lo Ne'emar. It doesn't just say cover it with dirt. אלא
בעפר, Ela Be'afar, in the dirt. ולמד שהשוחט צריך שיתן עפר למטה
ובעפר למעלה. u-lamad she-ha-shochet tzarich she-yitein afar le-mata u-ve-afar le-ma'ala. You have
to put the dirt below and above. So גמרא Gemara says דמזמינא
ליה עפר דכוליה פתקא. de-mazmina lei afar de-chulei pitka. So you basically,
yeah, you spread out dirt in the entire valley there where he
was doing his hunting. So wherever he would שוחט shochet the bird,
the blood would drop on some type of a, saw, you know,
whatever loose dirt that he had spread there so that he can
do כיסוי הדם. kisui ha-dam. So this is a little... one wonders
if one can really take this literally. Yes, Charlie.
If you fail to cover the blood of a חיה chaya or
an עוף, of, can you still eat the...?
Yes, it's a separate מצוה, mitzvah, but yes. Okay, Yosef. If he's
like near or something like
that that he's shooting the arrow, there's obviously time.
Well, there's time from when it leaves his hand, but so the
real question would be, is the fact that he's not holding it,
you know, when it's doing it, is that a problem? So we're
going to see that in the next משנה. mishna. It does not
actually need the person to...
the technical term is it doesn't need מעשה גברא, ma'aseh gavra, it
needs כוח גברא, koach gavra, meaning you don't actually have to, you
know, physically be manipulating the שחיטה shechita knife, it just has to
be coming from your energy. So yes, if you actually... the גמרא
Gemara is going to have a case, you had the animal's neck
sort of laying down and you sort of dropped the knife, we're
even going to talk about releasing the knife, right? And let's say
it just went down, that would actually be a good שחיטה. shechita.
What about electronic? What about doing it electronically? Right.
You mean like שחיטה, shechita, pushing a button? So the problem becomes,
and that is a very good question and this gets asked by
a wide range of issues about the whole use of
machines, machine-made מצה, matzah, this comes up a lot, which is how
far do you take the idea of כוח גברא? koach gavra? It's
one thing to say that I actually take my energy and communicate
it, you know, put it into, I'm talking, you know, the arrow,
right? I mean, and so that actually is my energy transmitted through
the air. That's one idea. The other thing is releasing. Now that's
a little different because the energy to fall down is actually the
gravity that's just taking over, but you know at least it's sort
of, I start by setting up the situation. How much if I
go ahead and I like push a button and then really the
energy for the continuation is coming through the, through the wires, how
much is that considered to be my כוח? koach? I mean, I
would say that it would be obvious for example that if you
went ahead and you got on let's say a bike and were
pedaling it and the energy went, and somehow that bike would communicate
again physical energy towards a machine, that would probably be totally fine.
If that bike creates, you know, create, is hooked up to a
generator, and then the generator feeds in electric wires, that's even more
removed. So there are those halachic questions at what stage do you
still consider something to be כוח גברא? koach gavra?
Degrees of separation? Yes, yes.
And whether here... so degree of separation is a concept of גרמא,
grama, direct or indirect. But this is making a greater demand of
כוח גברא, koach gavra, it needs your energy. So how far do
we explain that? But you know even gravity does, can be incorporated
into your כוח, koach, which we'll see later by releasing a knife,
so the lines are not always that clear. One minute, David has
his hand up before. What, David? Okay, Michael yes.
I'm just recalling what you said on Sunday. He said that the
reason why the knives are designed in such a way so the
blade goes all the way to the very end so you're actually
holding onto the blade the whole time when you actually do it,
so it would seem to speak against, you know, this... I mean
practically, against shooting the arrow because...
Obviously you don't want people to do this.
No, no, no, meaning... but you know, isn't there like a שהיה
shehiya kind of thing and you know, yes not necessarily a problem
of שהיה, shehiya, but you know but practically we just want you
to be holding the blade the entire time, in which case then
shooting the arrow...
I agree, that's what I'm saying,
practically yes, but now we're talking about theoretically.
Okay? Alright, so let's take a look. היה שוחט והתיז, haya shochet
ve-hitti, so you chopped off the head, there's a problem of דריסה
drisa that you might have, you know, because it was pressure if
you did the whole thing and chopped off the whole head. So
אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, and but then it says in
general though, or in general to avoid the problem of chopping off
the whole head as being a problem, the knife has to go,
has to be the width of the neck. So the question is
how do I... I told you what the גמרא's Gemara conclusion is
but the גמרא's Gemara going to figure out what that phrase means.
So let's take a look. אמר רבי זירא Amar Rabbi Zeira מלא
צואר וחוץ לצואר. melo tzavar ve-chutz la-tzavar. So it's not enough that
the knife be the width of the neck, and again you're only
doing one direction, you're not doing back and forth, it has to
be the width of the neck plus it has to extend beyond
the width of the neck. So איבעיא להו, iba'ei lehu, they raised
the question, מלא צואר וחוץ לצואר כמלא צואר? melo tzavar ve-chutz la-tzavar
ke-melo tzavar? How much does it have to extend beyond the width
of the neck? The width of the neck plus an additional neck
width outside, so two neck widths? או דלמא, o dilma, or do
we say מלא צואר וחוץ
לצואר משהו? melo tzavar ve-chutz la-tzavar mashehu?
It has to be the width of the neck plus a little
bit outside? Because again the משנה mishna was not clear, it just
said the width of the neck. So does that mean that's how
much it has to be in addition, a double amount, or just
that plus a little bit?
What is he bringing from anyway?
דחוץ... de-chutz... מלא צואר.
melo
tzavar.
Well let's, not clear, if he reads it the way that it's
that's referring to the amount outside the neck, then it's just what
the משנה's mishnah saying. So let's see what the גמרא's gemara answer
is. תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear. השוחט והתיז שני ראשים
בבת אחת, ha-shocheit v'hetiz shnei rashim b'vat achat,
so you did two heads at the same time. אם יש לסכין
מלא צואר אחד כשר, im yesh lasakin malei tzavar echad kasher,
so if it has the width of one neck, it is כשר.
kasher. So that's not our משנה, mishnah, that's a ברייתא, baraita, but
let's take a look at what that means.
I'm sorry, no it is our משנה, mishnah, I'm sorry, I'm sorry,
I slipped. Okay, so it was השוחט והתיז שני ראשים אם יש
לסכין מלא צואר
אחד כשר, ha-shocheit v'hetiz shnei rashim im yesh lasakin malei tzavar echad
kasher, that's
correct. I think I might have misread it when I read the
משנה, mishnah, I'm sorry. Anyway, so anyway, so if you slaughtered and
you cut off two heads, it is כשר. kasher.
מאי מלא צואר אחד? mai malei tzavar echad? What does it mean
the width of one neck? אילימא מלא צואר אחד ותו לא, ileima
malei tzavar echad v'tu lo, just the width of one neck? השתא
בבהמה אחת בעינן מלא צואר וחוץ לצואר, hashtah b'vehema achat beinan malei
tzavar v'chutz latzavar, so how could that be? If by one animal
you need the width of the neck plus a little bit going
beyond, בשתי בהמות סגי ליה כמלא צואר אחד? b'shtei beheimot sagi lei
k'malei tzavar echad? So how could this say that if you're doing
two heads, it's enough to have one neck width, if in general
we say you need one neck width plus a little bit? So
when it says by two heads you need one neck width, it
can't mean the total length is one neck width because that would
be even less than the normal length of a knife.
אלא פשיטא, ela peshita, what does it mean when it says if
you're doing two heads you need one neck width? פשיטא, peshita, it
means מלא צואר חוץ לשני צוארים. malei tzavar chutz lishnei tzavarim. It
means you need one neck width in addition to the two necks
that you're cutting.
שמע מינה מלא צואר חוץ לצואר, shma mina malei tzavar chutz latzavar,
so you see it means that when we say you need the
neck width, it means outside of the width of the neck, so
you need two neck widths. שמע מינה, shma mina, you hear that
from there. I
know, but let me just look at the משנה mishnah again.
I think I skipped that line in the משנה, mishnah, but okay,
I'm sorry, I apologize for that. But anyway, the משנה mishnah said,
I apologize for skipping that line, the משנה mishnah says if you're
cutting one neck, you need the width of the neck. If you're
cutting two necks, you need the width of a neck. Now, it
could be the simple way actually to read that משנה mishnah is
whether you're cutting one neck or two, it's enough to have the
knife the width of a neck. But Rabbi Zeira is asserting that
no, even when the משנה mishnah says the width of a neck,
you need that plus a little bit. So again, as Michael says,
where is he getting that from? Who knows? You need plus something,
it's not clear how much plus, a little or double. But he's
saying it's not just the width of a neck. But then the
גמרא gemara says okay, that's what Rabbi Zeira said by one neck.
How does the משנה mishnah go on and say by two necks
it's enough just to have the width of a
neck? There, if even by one neck you need a width plus
a little, by two necks you should certainly need more. So it
must be that the phrase in the משנה mishnah 'you need a
neck's width' is beyond the necks that you're actually cutting. So what
does that mean? It means the דיוק diyuk from the משנה mishnah
and whatever is not so good, let's just focus on the conclusion.
It means if you're cutting one neck and it's two neck-widths, so
even by going in one motion, right,
you're cutting it essentially twice, which is the same as going back
and forth. Okay, if it's two neck-widths, you need it to be
three lengths. Why? Because if you're only going to do one motion.
Because if you only do one motion, so if you're only doing
one motion, right, this one here on the outside is only going
to get the cutting of, right, one knife, two knife-widths. That last
one will get the cutting of three knife-widths, right? This will get
three knife-widths, right? But this one on the outside will only get
two if it's the width of the neck plus another width. So
the basic point is you have to go the width of the
neck twice, so if you're only going to move in one direction,
it has to be the width of the neck plus another width.
Depends on where you start.
I mean if you start from the very edge of the knife,
everyone would still get at least two neck widths, even... Well, that's
true. I mean in theory you could start the knife on the
outside and not hold it like this. Yeah, but again we're assuming
you're doing a total horizontal movement, so you're going to lay it
along the width. Okay, let's finish this up in terms of
the this משנה. mishnah. בזמן שהוליך ולא הביא, bizman she-holich v'lo heivi,
when did it have to be this double length? If you go
in one direction and not back and forth. ואם הוליך והביא, v'im
holich v'heivi, but if you go back and forth, it can even
be a small and again we're not concerned about pressure. אמר רב
מנשיא, amar Rav Menashia, and it says you can even use an
awl. בזימלא שאין לו קרניים, b'zimla she-ein lo karnayim, an awl that
does not have horns. Apparently they would sometimes make decorative awls or
whatever, you know, and they would have an awl and I guess
sometimes you see that on these like movies like with Vikings or
whatever, you know, they'd have a knife but they'd have like these
like, you know, pokey things on the handle, you know what I
mean? Like the handle has like a flat part and then it
could have like some horn-like things coming up. Okay, so that apparently
they had by these awls. But we have to make sure that
that's not the awl you're using because then we're afraid that the
horns are going to do tear the
סימנים. simanim. אמרו ליה רב אחא בריה דרב אויא לרב מנשיא, amrei
lei Rav Acha brei d'Rav Avya l'Rav Menashia, מחטא מאי? machta mai?
What if
it
is not an
awl, what if
it
is a מחטא machta which
רש״י Rashi says it's a... well actually... What? A needle? It calls
it a מחטא Machta a needle?
Aha,
that's what it means,
like a מחט Machat is a needle. Yeah, though רש"י Rashi says
that it is, that's interesting. I mean that may be indicating the
point, but רש"י Rashi says מרצע. Martzea. It translates איזמל Izamel as
an awl.
Do they have a picture? Do you think they have a picture
of it over there?
איזמל Izamel is an awl.
מחטא Machta is an awl.
No, I'm not saying מחטא Machta is a needle.
And איזמל Izamel is an awl.
Would there be a picture of it?
You can check, I don't think so. Okay, anyway the point being
that the מחטא, Machta, which as you're right, from מחט Machat probably
is what it is, anyway it's something that you normally use
for cutting through stabbing.
איזמל Izamel is probably a scalpel.
Scalpel. Okay. All right. So what?
Isn't the knife used for מילה Milah called an איזמל? Izamel?
That's true.
Yeah, that in some places is called an איזמל. Izamel. That's true.
Okay, so let's take a look. Anyway the difference is that this
second one is something that is very traditionally classically used more for
stabbing than for slicing. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so he said, מחטא
מבזע בזע, Machta Mivza Baze, a מחטא Machta tears, it doesn't cut.
Exactly, it's used for stabbing, not for slicing.
מחטא דאושכפי מאי, Machta De'ushkapi Mai, how about if it's this מחטא,
Machta, this needle, this awl that is used רש"י Rashi says for
in certain types of
what do you call it, in certain types of like leather cutting
where that actually is an awl that is used for cutting. אמר
ליה תנינא, Amar Lei Tanina, we learned in our משנה, Mishna, אפילו
כל שהוא, Afilu Kol Shehu, even the smallest amount.
מאי לאו מחטא דאושכפי, Mai Lav Machta De'ushkapi, isn't it even this
awl or needle of leather cutting which is very small but actually
does
slice? Someone says לא, no, it's an איזמל. Izamel. It would be
referring again to this איזמל Izamel which is an awl or a
scalpel. You've got a picture of him שחיטה shechting the bird? Lovely.
Okay, anyway איזמל, Izamel, so that scalpel or whatever, בהדיא קתני לה,
Behadya Katani La, that's explicit in the משנה. Mishna. פירושי קמפרש, Peirushei
Kamifaresh, it's explaining. מאי כל שהוא, Mai Kol Shehu, what does a
כל שהוא Kol Shehu mean? איזמל. Izamel. That even if it's an
איזמל. Izamel. הכא נמי מסתברא, Hacha Nami Mistabra, that makes sense. דאי
סלקא דעתך מחטא דאושכפי, De'isalka Da'atach Machta De'ushkapi, if it was this
awl of these leather makers, השתא מחטא דאושכפי שריא, Hashta Machta De'ushkapi
Sharya, if you would allow that even though it comes from a
class of awls that sometimes is, you know, does stabbing, you would
allow the one thing that is cutting, because that's the גמרא's Gemara
concern here. Can we let you use this awl or this needle
or whatever that other things that are just like this are used
for stabbing? Even if this one is used for cutting, there's a
reasonable concern that if we let you use this one, you'll come
to use the other ones and the other ones are invalid because
they're stabbing and not cutting. So if the משנה Mishna is saying
that that's good, this one that's from this, you know, this needle-like
thing, איזמל איבעיא, Izamel Ibaya, how much more so, you know, it's
obvious that you could use this איזמל. Izamel. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, not necessarily. איזמל איצטריכא ליה, Izamel Itztaricha Lei, I might
have thought that you, that it's not so obvious you could use
an איזמל. Izamel. Why not? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka Da'atach Amina, I
might have thought, ליגזר איזמל שאין לו קרניים אטו איזמל שיש לו
קרניים, Ligzar Izamel She'ein Lo Kranayim Atu Izamel She'yesh lo Kranayim, maybe
I won't let you use even an איזמל Izamel without these horns
because maybe it'll come to you accidentally using an איזמל Izamel with
these horns. קא משמע לן, Kamashma Lan, so the משנה Mishna is
telling us we're not concerned. So the גמרא Gemara here did not
at all focus on the size that the blade can be a
כל שהוא, Kol Shehu, which in my mind is a big חידוש,
Chiddush, right? Because if the blade is a כל שהוא, Kol Shehu,
right, you know, you might have to go back and forth like
a couple of times in order to cut through, but that's apparently
the point. If you only want to do one movement, it has
to be double length. If you're going to do a back and
forth movement, it can be, it can be small, and we're not
concerned that the back and forth is going to lead to pressure.
So that's the idea of כל שהוא. Kol Shehu. And then the
only question it got to is let's say you have these small
little blades. So let's say it's sometimes, you know, it's from a
type of blade that often is used for stabbing and not cutting.
Do we, and slicing, do we allow you to use that or
we're afraid that if we let you use that, you'll use the
ones that are only used for stabbing? That was the question about
the מחטא. Machta. The question about the איזמל Izamel is why the
משנה Mishna had to point out that that's okay is because sometimes
they come with these decorative horns. So maybe if we let you
use the one without the horns, you'll come to use the one
with the horns and that'll lead to tear. So those are these
sort of cluster of concerns, but the basic חידוש Chiddush is even
a כל שהוא Kol Shehu is enough. Okay, yes.
So why are we not concerned that if even it's a little
bit that going back and forth won't lead to pressure? I do
not know.
It seems, I agree with you, it seems to be a very
reasonable concern. Right. And in the one שחיטה Shechita I saw in
Senegal where they actually slaughtered this goat, that's what they did. And
I was actually quite surprised. They took a, I mean I don't
know how long the knife was, but they actually did a back
and forth like that and it was a little disturbing, you know,
because you imagine that that's got to be not pleasant.
So I don't know. I don't know. I mean that. That's the
חידוש chidush of the משנה, mishna, but you're right.
That's not, for whatever reason I can't always say why we have
certain concerns and why we don't. Okay, now we get to the
next משנה, mishna, which actually very nicely ties into this whole issue
about the shooting of the arrows and the כח גברא koach gavra
that was just discussed. Let's take a look. נפלה סכין ושחטה. nafla
sakin veshachata. The knife fell off the table and it shechted. It
was an animal that was, I mean you have to try to
imagine what the physics are that this is exactly going to work,
but somehow the animal's neck was exactly like a perpendicular to the
ground, I mean you know because it can't, because the, you know,
perpendicular to the ground or something, so that when the knife fell
off, the blade cut it in the right motion. Anyway, somehow that
happened, so it's not good. אף על פי ששחטה כדרכה, af al
pi sheshachata kedarka, although the cut and the slicing and everything technically
you know was correct, פסולה, psula, it's invalid. Now why? שנאמר וזבחת
ואכלת, shenemar vezavachta veachalta, you shall slaughter and you shall eat. מה
שאתה זובח אתה אוכל. ma sheata zoveach ata ochel.
What you slaughter you can eat. It requires it be a human
act, not that it just be that it got slaughtered, but there
was an act of slaughter. There was a slaughterer, yes.
Was there a case earlier in the in this tractate where a
knife was thrown and it shechted an animal and... Rabbi Yoshi? Yes.
Well, we're going to discuss that. Okay, but yes, but that's just
like also the arrow and
that's coming with
כח גברא, koach gavra, which is exactly the point. So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. טעמא דנפלה. tama denafla. The reason
of the משנה mishna is that it fell on its own. הא
הפילה, ha hipila, if you made it fall, like I said you
released it and it fell down, כשרה, ksheira, if you did that,
it's valid. So now, A, that points out this issue about כח
גברא, koach gavra, right, like the arrow, you don't need to hold
it, you just need to have sort of you know thrown it
or released it or whatever communicated your energy to it. But the
גמרא Gemara now has another point. ואף על גב דלא מכוין. veaf
al gav dela michavein. Let's forget the issue of the act for
a moment. Presumably all these cases are it was not intentional, right?
So the משנה's mishna concern is, did you do it or did
it come from the table? But in either scenario it sounds like
there was it was not intended, right? So now we have another
point. שחיטה shechita is not requiring intent.
דלא בעי כוונה.
dela
bei kavana. Right, well that's what we're going to discuss.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מאן תנא דלא בעי כוונה לשחיטה. man
tana dela bei kavana lishchita. Who is the תנא tanna that you
don't require intent for שחיטה? shechita? אמר רבא רבי נתן היא. amar
Rava Rabbi Natan hi. It's רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. דתני אושעיא זעירא
דמנחברייא. detani Oshaya Zeira demin Chavraya. The younger אושעיא Oshaya from the
בני ישיבה, Bnei Yeshiva, that's what רש"י Rashi also says חברייא Chavraya
means, taught the following.
זרק סכין לנעצה בכותל. zarak sakin linoatza bakotel. So here you go,
this is what we were talking about. You threw a knife and
you were playing darts or whatever, you were trying to throw the
knife against the wall, והלכה ושחטה כדרכה. vehalcha veshachata kedarka. And again
this animal was exactly situated so that as the knife was moving
it shechted it כדרכה, kedarka, it shechted it. So you have your
כח גברא, koach gavra, your energy, you're throwing the knife, but there's
obviously no intention. רבי נתן מכשיר. Rabbi Natan machshir. רבי נתן Rabbi
Natan says fine, you don't need intention for שחיטה. shechita. וחכמים פוסלין.
vechachamim poslin. The rabbis invalidate. Okay, so now again, thus normally for
something to be considered an act, we normally do assume two criteria.
Number one is that you're doing it, it's coming from you or
your energy. If it's an act, a human act. And the other
two is that it's intentional. If it's not intentional then it's considered
like מתעסק, mitasek, right? It just happens by itself almost, it's not
considered connected to you. So here is a very interesting חידוש chidush
that maybe you do require כח גברא koach gavra but you would
not actually require intention, and that normally is the second thing that
goes around with defining an act. That's what רבי נתן Rabbi Natan
says. וחכמים פוסלין, vechachamim poslin, and the חכמים Chachamim invalidate. So, הוא
תני לה והוא אמר לה. hu tani la vehu amar la. He
taught this ברייתא Baraita and he also commented on it. הלכה כרבי
נתן. halacha keRabbi Natan. We rule like רבי נתן Rabbi Natan that
שחיטה's shechita not, does not require intention. So the גמרא Gemara says,
והא אמר רבא חדא זימנא. veha amar Rava chada zimna. Didn't רבא
Rava already tell us this point? דתנן, detnan, way back to our
first משנה, mishna, וכולן ששחטו ואחרים רואים אותם שחיטתן כשרה. vekulan sheshachatu
veacherim roim otam shechitatan ksheira. If a minor, חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh
shote vekatan, right a minor, a deaf-mute and the and the, you
know, insane person, whatever, shecht and other people observe them, it's valid
as long as it's technically correct.
ואמרינן, veamrinan, and we said, מאן תנא דלא בעי כוונה. man tana
dela bei kavana. Who is the תנא tanna that does not require
כוונה? kavana? At the time we pointed out it's a little funny
that it's calling that lack of כוונה. kavana. Because normally we assume
that a קטן katan can have כוונה kavana that accompanies an action,
an action, but nevertheless we're now framing it as lack of כוונה.
kavana. So how how is that good? What about כוונה? kavana? ולשחיטה.
velishchita. ואמר רבא, veamar Rava, רבי נתן היא. Rabbi Natan hi. It's
רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. So now רבא, Rava, why does רבא Rava
have to sort of make this point on two separate משניות? mishnayot?
So the גמרא Gemara
says, צריכא. tzricha. He needs to make the point twice. דאי אשמעינן
התם. dei ashmeinan hatam. Had he just made the point on the
first משנה, mishna, משום דקא מכוין לשום חתיכה בעולם. mishum deka michavein
lishum chaticha baolam.
Because the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shote vekatan we're not saying they
have no intention, at least they're intending to cut. They might not
intend, I mean if they're there, they're holding the animal, they're taking
their knife, they're shechting, clearly they're trying to cut the סימנים. simanim.
תוספות Tosafot says it's not just cut, they realize that they're cutting
a trachea and esophagus, they're realizing they're cutting the סימנים. simanim. So
what lack of כוונה kavana do they have? Whether they can sufficiently
intend to effect שחיטה, shechita, meaning for it to effect a halachic
change. Now this actually is very nice because this helps reframe... the
issues when we dealt with קטן. katan. Remember at the time we
said that a קטן katan actually can intend to do the physical
act. The problem with a קטן katan is דעת, das, to have
the, actually, it's what's, to either have the intention or for the
הלכה halacha to recognize the intention to effect halachic change. That I'm
going to through this act, you know, make this woman my wife,
or I'm going to purchase this object. It's not just my physical
act, but the broader implications of it. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara is here actually admitting. That yes, we will say the קטן
katan knows that he is cutting the סימנים. simanim. The question is,
is he really able to intend for the implications of what שחיטה
shechita is. Can he define this שחיטה? shechita? He can certainly define
it as the cutting of the trachea and the esophagus, but does
he understand the concept of שחיטה shechita enough as a הלכה halacha
concept to understand that he's doing an act of שחיטה. shechita. So
that was the problem there. That's not a huge lack of כוונה,
kavana, that's a very narrow lack of כוונה. kavana. אבל הכא, aval
hacha, but here, דלא קמכווין, delo kamichavein, you have no intention at
all to cut, you're just throwing it at the wall. אימא לא,
eima lo, maybe it's completely not good because there's no intention to
cut at all. ואי אשמעינן הכא, ve-i ashmeinan hacha, if it just
said it here, משום דקאתי מכח בן דעת, mishum dekasi mikach ben
das, at least it's coming from the energy of an adult, of
somebody who is considered a, you know, an adult in הלכה. halacha.
אבל התם, aval hasam, but by the case by the קטן, katan,
דלא קאתי מכח בן דעת, delo kasi mikach ben das, it's not
coming through an actor who is considered to be an adult or
of right mind, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe it's not good, צריכא.
tzricha. And that is part of the חידוש chiddush by the קטן,
katan, because maybe it's not a question of כוונה, kavana, maybe שחיטה
shechita just requires for it to be a halachic act that's an
act performed by somebody who has, you know, general standing within הלכה,
halacha, which is an adult and somebody of right mind. So actually
both are telling you something. There it's not telling you such a
חידוש chiddush of כוונה, kavana, the lack of כוונה kavana there is
relatively minor, excuse the pun, there it's telling you that you don't
need an act to be performed by an adult or by somebody
of right mind, and right, because if you say a human act,
maybe it requires like somebody who's acknowledged to be an actor in
הלכה, halacha, and here it's telling you that even if there was
basically no כוונה kavana at all, which is also a huge חידוש,
chiddush, because you're right, here where you're just throwing it against the
wall, you might call it מתעסק, misoisek, it's completely incidental what happened.
So it's actually quite a surprise how little you need for שחיטה.
shechita. You need human energy, but you don't need an adult actor
and you don't need to have any intention. Okay, so let's see
where the גמרא Gemara now goes on with this, because the גמרא
Gemara uses this as an opportunity to discuss general questions of כוונה
kavana in הלכה, halacha, and which actions require intention and do not
require intention. So let's take a look. איתמר, itmar, it was taught.
נדה שנאנסה וטבלה, nidda shene'ensa vetavla, a נדה, nidda, a woman who
is a נדה, nidda, who was forced and put into the מקוה.
mikva. So what does that mean? So it could mean as we'll
say that maybe, you know, her friends took her and threw her
into a מקוה, mikva, or it means that she was walking by
the seashore and a wave hit her and that wave would constitute
a legitimate מקוה. mikva. But somehow she was not trying to go
to the מקוה, mikva, she just fell in. Is that a good
טבילה tvila if it was without any intention? Okay, so what's the
הלכה? halacha? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
טהורה לביתה, tehora leveisa, she's permissible to her household, which means to
her husband, ואסורה לאכול בתרומה, ve-asura leechol betruma, but she cannot eat
תרומה, truma, because we're going to assume and there're actually משניות mishnayos
about this, that when one wants to go to the מקוה mikva
to be purified to eat קדשים, kodshim, to eat תרומה, truma, to
eat sacrifices, you need to have intention that this is going to
make me טהור tahor for תרומה, truma, going to make me טהור
tahor for sacrifices. So we know when it comes to those laws
of טומאה וטהרה, tumah vetahara, intention is required. It might only be
דרבנן, derabbanan, but whatever the point is, there we know intention matters.
But how about the other aspects? So if she wants to eat
תרומה, truma, that's not okay, she needed intention. But how about if
she wants to now be with her husband? That is okay. ורבי
יוחנן אמר, ve-Rabbi Yochanan amar, אף לביתה לא טהורה. af leveisa lo
tehora. No, even for her husband, it's all one package. And since
it's about טומאה, tumah, and טומאה tumah requires intention, then even, you
know, for קדשים kodshim or whatever, that even for הטהרה, ha-taharah, right?
Okay. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, amar leh Rava le-Rav Nachman, so
רבא Rava said to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, לרב דאמר טהורה לביתה
ואסורה לאכול בתרומה, le-Rav de-amar tehora leveisa ve-asura leechol betruma, according to
רב Rav that distinguishes these categories, I don't get it, he says.
עון כרת הותרה איסור מיתה מבעיא, avon kareis hutra issur misa mibaia,
if you're allowing the כרת kareis prohibition, which is the prohibition of
a נדה, nidda, of a man of a woman and a man
to have sex when the woman is a נדה, nidda, that's a
prohibition of כרת, kareis, so certainly you should permit the מיתה. misa.
Now מיתה misa here does not mean by the court, but it
means מיתה, misa, heavenly death, which is what the תורה Torah ascribes
to the sin of eating תרומה truma when you are טמא, tamei,
which is considered to be less bad than כרת. kareis. כרת kareis
is you're going to die and your kids are going to die.
מיתה misa is just you're going to die. So if this טבילה's
tvila good enough without intention to work to, you know, remove the
prohibition of כרת, kareis, it should certainly remove the prohibition of eating
תרומה, truma, which is a prohibition of מיתה. misa. אמר ליה, amar
leh, he said back to him, no, it's not about, it's not
everything is about weight of prohibition. בעלה חולין הוא, ba'alah chullin hu,
her husband is חולין, chullin, is lay matters, is not about sanctified
objects. ובחולין לא בעי כוונה, uvechullin lo ba'ei kavana, when it comes
to lay matters, you do not need כוונה. kavana. And this then
becomes the basic point, which we'll see obviously ties in for our
משנה. Mishnah. That means
it's
interesting again how when the גמרא Gemara decides to have, to have,
oh, that's a good point, מסכת חולין. Masechet Chullin. When the גמרא
Gemara decides to abstract, when things are local requirements and when things
are considered universal, but here it's saying when you need an act
to change halakhic status, so as long as it doesn't relate to
קדשים Kodshim or to תרומה, Truma, to things like, to things that
are in the קדשים Kodshim sphere, then that act suffices without כוונה.
kavana. Whether the act is שחיטה, shechting, whether it's going to the
מקוה, mikveh, whatever an act is that changes halakhic status, that does
not require intention. The only time you require intention for an act
is when it relates to issues of קדשים. Kodshim. That we know
from other משניות, mishnayot, and even that might be rabbinic, but at
least that's the only place. Anything that's חולין, chullin, so even by
a נדה, nidah, he's saying I can split my vote. Okay, and
then it raises interesting questions about the other opinion. Does the other
opinion fundamentally disagree by חולין chullin or fundamentally agree but say by
a נדה nidah it's all one package? Okay, now let's take a
look. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to look at this as
a general question. Well, we sort of will, but first we're going
to focus on the general question about whether and we'll generalize. So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: וחולין
לא בעי כוונה? Vechullin lo ba'ei kavana? And are you telling me
חולין chullin does not require intention? ומנא תימרא? Uminat teimreih? Where do
you know that from? דתנן, Detnan, we taught in a משנה. Mishnah.
גל שנתלש ובו ארבעים סאה. Gal shenitlash uvo arbaim se'ah.
So you have a wave in an ocean, and somebody's walking by
the seashore and the wave sort of detaches from the sea. Does
this ever happen? I can't imagine this. Maybe if it hits against
a rock, maybe you can have a huge tsunami. But tsunami is
from the ocean? Yeah, but it's just the wind causes like big
chunks like big... earthquake. Oh, so that causes, oh I see, so
that causes like a big quantity of water to separate from the
ocean. No, it's still attached to the rest of the ocean.
No, so it has to be separated from the ocean.
That's
the חידוש chiddush is that it's separate from the ocean. I guess
somebody I guess if a wave hit a rock, right, then a
lot would spray up. Okay, anyway, all right, so if it has
ארבעים סאה, arbaim se'ah, it's a kosher מקוה. mikveh. ונפל על אדם
ועל כלים. Venafal al adam ve'al kelim.
And it fell on the seashore by a person and vessels that
were standing there. טהורים. Tehorim. So they're kosher, they're טהור tahor because
they went into a מקוה. mikveh. The מקוה mikveh was the seawater
that now hit them.
Waterfalls would qualify.
A waterfall, but that would be attached. We're trying to get a
case of detached or those because that's the requirement of ארבעים סאה.
arbaim se'ah. If it's still attached, obviously the whole ocean have it.
Okay, anyway, they've just now gone into a מקוה. mikveh.
You mean you saying if it was attached then of course it
would be okay?
Yeah, you wouldn't need it wouldn't be like such a חידוש. chiddush.
It'd be less, of course it's okay, it'd be less of a
חידוש. chiddush. Because it's detached you have to say there's ארבעים סאה.
arbaim se'ah. Okay. מאי לאו אדם דומיא דכלים? Mai lav adam dumya
dekelim? So are we not talking about the situation by the person
was like those vessels? מה כלים דלא מכווני, Ma kelim delo mechavnei,
the same way the vessels had no intention when the water hit
them, אף אדם נמי, af adam nami, so לא בעי כוונה? lo
ba'ei kavana? Even the person, now of course why do you even
just prove it from the vessels? So once you see a מקוה
mikveh works for vessels without intention, it just happened, it should work
for people. So anyway, maybe we are saying that. We're saying look,
here's a case nobody had intention, it worked. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ממאי? Mimmay? Who tells you? דילמא ביושב ומצפה עסקינן. Dilma beyoshev
umetzappeh askinan. You're there sitting by the seashore waiting to be hit
by a wave so that you don't have to go to the
מקוה. mikveh. So therefore maybe you do have intention. One minute. אימתי
יתלש הגל? Eimatai yitlash hagal? When will the wave come and hit
me? וכלים דומיא דאדם. Vekelim dumya de'adam. And the vessels are just
like you. מה אדם דבעינן כוונה, Ma adam dbe'inan kavana, maybe the
same way you require intention, meaning you could argue that you do
require intention, אף כלים נמי דקמכוין להו. af kelim nami dkamechaven lehu.
And the vessels also require intention. Now not they can't intend, they're
vessels, but the same way you need to intend when you put
them in the מקוה. mikveh. And here too you're intending that you're
waiting for the wave to hit you. דקמכוין להו אדם. Dkamechaven lehu
adam. So וכי תימא, vechi teima, lest you say ביושב ומצפה מאי
למימרא? beyoshev umetzappeh mai lemimra? If you're intending for it to work
then what's the חידוש? chiddush? Of course it works when a wave
hits you. I don't know, of course anyway. So מהו דתימא, ma
dteima, אימא למיגזר eima litchzar משום חרדלית של גשמים. mishum chardelis shel
geshamim.
Let's be concerned that it won't be a wave. If we let
you do this, you'll also do it in a downpour. Now why
would it be good and bad in a downpour? Well you could
see if it's just downpour of individual drops obviously because it's not
hitting you at one time. But let's say there's a rain, a
flood of rain and it let's say comes off of a mountaintop
or a rooftop, right, you're walking under a rooftop during a rain
and you get hit by a wave of rainwater. Why would that
not be good? Because very important הלכה, halakhah, a מקוה mikveh has
to be standing water, it cannot be moving water. That's even why
if there are cracks in the מקוה mikveh wall and that causes
the water to sort of move or whatever, question how do you
define moving. If it moves back and forth is it okay? But
anyway, it certainly can't be moving to another location. The exception is
natural bodies of water. Okay, a מעיין, ma'ayan, a well, an ocean,
a river, these types of things can be moving. So therefore this
thing hits you, it's moving, that's okay if it's ocean water or
if it's river water. It's not okay if it's rainwater off of
a
roof. Maybe I should be concerned that if I let you go
into the מקוה mikvah by this wave that hit you, when the
head of the wave hit you, you'll come to do it even
in the arc of the wave. The crest. Why is that a
problem? Because a מקוה mikvah also can't be in midair. A מקוה
mikvah has to be on the ground. So if you're standing and
the head of the wave hits you, as it's hitting you it's
also connecting to the ground. That's considered like the מקוה mikvah is
on the ground. But if the wave, you know, there was crest,
was sort of up in the air and you threw something into
the crest, not the head that was hitting the ground, that wouldn't
be good. So I might have had to have those גזירות, gezeiras,
קמשמלן דלא גזרינן, kamashmalan de'lo gazrinan, so telling me we don't do
it. ומנא תימא דלא מטבילין בכיפין, uminatema de'lo matbilin bekif, how do
you know that you can't go into the sort of the, you
know, the crest of it, as crest is right or the arc
of it, anyway, the stuff that's not touching the ground? דתנן, detnan,
because we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, מטבילין בראשים ואין מטבילין בכיפין.
matbilin berashim ve'ein matbilin bekifin. You can do, you can go into
a מקוה, mikvah, you can be טובל tovel in the head of
a wave, the head that's hitting the ground, but not in the
arc of the wave. Why? שאין מטבילין באוויר, she'ein matbilin ba'avir, because
you don't, you can't go to the מקוה mikvah in midair. Okay,
so מקוה mikvah has to be attached. Now, what's the אפשט apshat
for us? The אפשט apshat is the simple case certainly is that
the person and the vessels became טהור tahor with no כוונה, kavana,
but we're saying no, maybe they had כוונה kavana and it's the
חידוש chidush is something else about not to be mixing it up
with rainwater and not going into the arc, but maybe it's a
case that they had כוונה. kavana. Now I do want to point
out that even if they had כוונה kavana here, it's a little
bit strange that if you, that if you do require כוונה, kavana,
כוונה kavana works. Because when I require כוונה, kavana, to some degree
that usually is attending my action. So if I am going to
dunk in a מקוה, mikvah, I am having כוונה kavana as I
lower myself into the water. Right? Or if I'm going to have
כוונה kavana for שחיטה, shechita, I'm having כוונה kavana as I move
the knife. In this type of a case, I'm sitting here and
having כוונה kavana and the wave is hitting me. So the fact
that I'm doing absolutely no action or the wave is hitting the
vessels and I'm just saying I want those vessels to, can you
say normally כוונה kavana is to define it as an act of
טבילה? tevila? What made this, you know, an act if there was
no action associated? Now maybe you could say the human being even
staying in your place is an action. That could be. So staying
here waiting for the wave, that's an act of טבילה. tevila. But
for the vessels, if I didn't put the vessels there, they happen
to be there and I'm just standing aside and saying I want
it to hit them, is that considered like I did an act
of being טובל tovel the vessels? Not so clear in my mind.
So even inserting כוונה kavana here is questionable if it really, you
know, is how we need כוונה kavana to operate. Because normally it's
not כוונה kavana as an independent criteria, it's part of defining something
as an intentional act. Okay, so that I do think is an
important question.
Well, I mean we have other cases like with the water and
you know, for הכשר זרעים, hechshir zera'im, right? You know, if you're
okay with it to do...
But that yes, that's true, but that's not necessarily about an act,
that's כי יותן ki yutan and that's yes, you're correct, there כוונה
kavana is more as an independent criteria.
Okay, so yeah, I don't see how these examples would immerse the
either the person or the vessels totally because it doesn't have to
be immersed?
Yes,
so what, it's a big wave.
But I'm saying they'd still be on the ground somewhere.
They're covered with water all around. Oh you mean the below them.
Oh yeah, so right, that's true, we would assume that there'd be
a thin film that would get underneath, that they would float up,
yes, something like that. Okay, so let's keep on going. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא חולין דלא בעי כוונה מנהלן? Elo
chullin de'lo ba'ei kavana meihaminallan?
So since you can't prove it from this case of the wave,
where are you going to show that חולין chullin does not require
intention? דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, פירות שנפלו תוך
אמת המים. Peiros shenafalu toch ammat hamayim. So there you go, like
very nice, but this is not about the הכשר זרעים, hechshir zera'im,
it's about the טבילה tevila that accompanies it. So fruit fell into
a, you know, into some type of a trough of water. And
this is again the issue that fruit is only susceptible for טומאה
tumah if it comes in contact with water that you wanted it
to come in contact with. Okay. ופשט מי שהוא טמא ונטלן, Upashat
mi shehu tamei venatalan, and you stuck your hands into this trough
of water to get the fruit.
So ידיו טהורות ופירות אינם בכי יותן, yadav tehoros upeiros einam bekhi
yutan, so your hands are טהורות tehoros because, because this trough of
water constitutes enough water, you don't need a full מקוה mikvah for
נטילת ידיים netilas yadayim which is a rabbinic concern. So going, putting
your hands in water constitutes purifying your hands. But the, and the
fruit are not susceptible for טומאה tumah because you don't want the
water, you didn't want the water to clean your hands, you didn't
want the water on your fruit, you just wanted to get the
fruit. So there's no desire for the water, so therefore the fruit
is not susceptible but your hands are טהור. tahor. So you see
you had no intention to clean or purify your hands and they're
still טהור. tahor. And now the משנה Mishnah continues and it says
the following: ואם בשביל שיודחו
ידיו, Ve'im bishvil sheyudachu yadav, so if you wanted the fruit, if
you wanted actually the fruit to be washed off or your hands
to be washed off, so ידיו טהורות, yadav tehoros, your hands are
still טהורות tehoros obviously because you're putting them into, actually רש"י Rashi
reads יודחו ידיו. yudachu yadav. but yeah, he must have had a
double ידיו. yadav. But anyway, if you wanted your hands to be
cleaned, it could have been the fruit. Anyway, your hands are טהורות
tehoros for obvious reasons, because you know, again, you stuck them in
water. ופירות בכי יותן upeiros bechi yutan but the fruit now is
also susceptible because you wanted either the fruit to become washed or
you wanted your hands to be washed which means you wanted the
water, and as long as you wanted the water and you wanted
it there with the fruit because it made it convenient for you
to wash off your hands, whatever it is, that's enough. Even desiring
the water not directly to be on the fruits, I won't go
into the details. The point for us is your hands are טהור
tahor without any intention. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara is done. So yes, you've proven it that
at least in that case we see at least when it comes
to נטילת ידים, netilas yadayim, now who knows if you can abstract
it and universalize it, but at least there you do not require
intention. But the גמרא Gemara is not done. איתיבי Eiseivei רבא Rava
לרב נחמן. le-Rav Nachman. So רבא Rava asked רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
טבל לחולין והוחזק לחולין אסור למעשר. taval l'chullin vehuchzak l'chullin asur l'maaser.
So again, רב נחמן Rav Nachman remembers the one who said by
the נידה niddah that she's אסור asur to her husband, that חולין
chullin does require intention. So here we have the following teaching: it
says that if you go into a מקוה mikvah and you're intending
to be טהור tahor for non-sanctified food and you are הוחזק, huchzak,
you're established for חולין, chullin, then you cannot eat מעשר maaser because
you only intended for non-sanctified food. So he says, הוחזק אין לא
הוחזק לא. huchzak in lo huchzak lo. I'm sorry, so this actually
רב נחמן Rav Nachman why'd he ask רב נחמן? Rav Nachman?
Oh, it was רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, excuse me, before.
Yeah, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, okay, fine. So whatever, רב נחמן Rav
Nachman is actually defending the one that says you do not need
כוונה. kavanah. So anyway, here you see that you went for the
מקוה mikvah for the intention of חולין, chullin, so only with the
intention of חולין chullin are you טהור; tahor; without that intention you
are not. So let's see what the answer is. לא הוחזק לא.
Lo huchzak lo. הכי קאמר, Hachi kaamar, no,
this is what it means: אף על פי שהוחזק לחולין, af al
pi shehuchzak l'chullin, even if you intended it to work for חולין
chullin and even if it was established for חולין, chullin, אסור למעשר,
asur l'maaser, you're still forbidden for מעשר. maaser. So it doesn't mean
you need it to be good for חולין, chullin, it just means
even if you have it, it does not work for מעשר שני.
maaser sheni. איתיבי, Eiseivei, okay, I'll ask you again, טבל ולא הוחזק
כאילו לא טבל. taval velo huchzak ke'ilu lo taval.
If you went to the מקוה mikvah and you were not established
for one thing, meaning you didn't intend for it to work for
a certain level, you might as well have not gone to the
מקוה. mikvah. So מאי לאו כאילו לא טבל כלל, mai lav ke'ilu
lo taval klal, does it not mean you know it didn't count
at all? לא כאילו לא טבל למעשר. Lo, ke'ilu lo taval l'maaser.
So no, it means that if you went, it doesn't work at
all for you know for higher levels, for מעשר, maaser, אבל טבל
לחולין. aval taval l'chullin.
But it does work for חולין. chullin. So again, it means if
you go for non-מעשר שני, maaser sheni, non-תרומה, terumah, non-קדשים kodshim purposes,
it doesn't
work, so for them it's like you didn't go at all, but
for חולין chullin it does count. הוא סבר דחויי קמדחי ליה. Hu
savar dichei kimidchi leh. He thought he was just you know pushing
him off, giving him a bad answer, because it really does sound
like the מקוה mikvah didn't do anything when you didn't have intention.
נפק דק ואשכח, Nafak dak v'ashkach, he went and he found the
following ברייתא. baraisa. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, baraisa, טבל
ולא הוחזק מותר לחולין ואסור למעשר. taval velo huchzak muttar l'chullin v'asur
l'maaser. It was very explicit that if you went to the מקוה
mikvah without intention, it works for חולין, chullin, does not work for
מעשר. maaser. So again, it's a little you know there the indications
seemed to go the other way, but in the end the גמרא
Gemara is saying that it once again proves for חולין chullin you
do not need כוונה. kavanah. So אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, amar
leh Abaye le-Rav Yosef, so אביי Abaye said to רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, לימא תהוי תיובתא דרבי יוחנן מהא? leima tehvei tiyufta de-Rabbi Yochanan
me-ha? So good, now that we have that ברייתא baraisa that explicitly
says that חולין chullin does not require כוונה, kavanah, that should be
a contradiction to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So אמר ליה, amar leh,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan הוא דאמר כרבי יונתן בן יוסף. hu de-amar
k'Rabbi Yonatan ben Yosef. No, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would go like, you're right, that does say you
do not need intention, but there's an explicit teaching that you do
need intention, like רבי יונתן בן יוסף. Rabbi Yonatan ben Yosef. דתניא,
Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, baraisa, רבי יונתן בן יוסף אומר
וכובס. Rabbi Yonatan ben Yosef omer v'chubas. This is about laundering the
clothes of when they have צרעת tzaraas on them. מה תלמוד לומר
שני? Mah talmud lomar sheni? Why does it say a second time?
Because once it says you wash it to see if the spot
will go away, then in the purification process you wash it again.
So why does it explicitly have to say again? מקיש תכבס שני
לתכבס ראשון, Makish tichabbes sheni l'tichabbes rishon,
to connect the second washing which is the purification to the first
washing. מה תכבס ראשון לדעת, Mah tichabbes rishon l'daas, the same way
the first washing is with the intention of the כהן, kohen, because
the כהן kohen says he commands the person to wash, אף תכבס
שני לדעת, af tichabbes sheni l'daas,
the second one which is to purify also requires intention. So you
see, to purify requires intention even when it's not for קדש. kodesh.
אימא הלן בעינן דעת כהן, Eima hallan be'inan daas kohen,
maybe the same way the first washing the כהן kohen you need
the intention of the כהן, kohen, he specifically commands it to be
washed, אף כאן בעינן דעת כהן, af kan be'inan daas kohen, maybe
here too? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar וטהר, v'taher,
it should become טהור tahor מכל מקום, mikkol makom, regardless. So there
is a teaching that says you do require intention even for חולין.
chullin. Let's just read two more lines. מתקיף לה רב שימי בר
אשי, Matkif lah Rav Shimi bar Ashi, ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי?
umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? How could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really
say you require intention for חולין? chullin? והאמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם
משנה, Ve-ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan halachah kistam mishnah, and we rule like every
סתם משנה. stam mishnah. ותנן, Utenan, and now just to sort of
get it back to our משנה, mishnah, נפלה סכין ושחטה אף על
פי ששחטה כדרכה פסולה, nafla sakkin v'shachata af al pi sheshachata k'darkah
pesulah, that when the knife fell and slaughtered, even though it slaughtered
properly, it is invalid. falls off it's invalid, ואבינא בה *Vavina bah*,
and we said on it, טעמא דנפלה *Ta'ama dinafla*, it's only when
it fell by itself, הא הפילה הוא כשרה *Ha hepila hu kshaira*,
if you dropped it it's kosher, אף על גב דלא מכוין *Af
al gav delo mechaven*, even though you don't have intention, okay, ואמרינן
*Ve'amrinan*, and we said, so this is a whole recap, מאן תנא
דלא בעי כוונה לשחיטה *Man tana delo ba'ei kavana lishchita*, who is
the one that doesn't require intention? אמר רבא רבי נתן היא *Amar
Rava Rebbe Natan hi*, Rebbe Natan he. So now basically we're now
just, you know, coming, you know, summing it up. So you're telling
me there's a debate if חולין *Chulin* requires intention? Isn't it clear
from our משנה *Mishna* by שחיטה *Shchita* that חולין *Chulin* does not
require intention when it's not about, you know, קדשים *Kodshim* and so
on? So he, so here's the answer. So he says, בשחיטה אפילו
רבי יונתן בן יוסף *Bishchita afilu Rebbe Yonatan ben Yosef*, in שחיטה
*Shchita*,
even the one that says you require intention, רבי יונתן בן יוסף
*Rebbe Yonatan ben Yosef*, would admit that שחיטה *Shchita* does not, it's
an exception. Why? מדיגלי רחמנא מתעסק בקדשים פסול *Midegali Rachmana mitasek bekodshim
pasul*, since the Torah tells us that when you are involved in
something else, when it's sacrifices, if you don't have intention by sacrifices,
you don't realize it's a קרבן *Korban*, you think it's a non-קרבן
*Korban*, you're doing something else, that that's a problem by קדשים *Kodshim*,
מכלל דלחולין לא בעינן כוונה *Michlal delachulin lo ba'inan kavana*. You see
that for חולין *Chulin*, you do not need כוונה *Kavana*. So basically
what the גמרא *Gemara* is saying is, by שחיטה *Shchita*, in contrast
to שחיטת קדשים *Shchitas kodshim*, שחיטת חולין *Shchitas chulin*, by everybody agrees
you do not require intention, and the question is can we generalize
that and say by all things or at least when it's coming
to change statuses by חולין *Chulin*, like טבילה *Tevila* and other types
of things also you do not require intention? We will pick up
here tomorrow discussing more precisely what intention are we talking about is
or is not required.